I know that everybody.
모두 다 알아요
It seems like just the other day that we were embarking on our quest together, and now here we are
함께 여정을 시작하던 게 엊그제 같은데 벌써 4주 차가
at the beginning of week four, rapidly approaching the halfway point.
시작됐고 여정의 절반이 빠르게 다가오고 있어요
So what is in store for us this time?
이번엔 어떤 일이 벌어질까요?
Uh, this week we are getting into an essential period of building core knowledge.
이번 주에는 핵심 지식을 쌓는 중요한 단계에 들어갈 거예요
It's going to be about this very challenging question that hits us all, which is we are spoilt for
우리 모두에게 닥치는 어려운 질문에 관한 내용일 거예요 우리는 선택권이 너무 많다는
choice.
거죠
There are so many llms out there.
llm이 너무 많아요
There are so many decisions to be made, closed source or open source.
오픈 소스냐 폐쇄 소스냐 결정할 게 너무 많아요
And and then in each category, so many.
각 카테고리에 정말 많아요
How do you pick the right LLM for a problem at hand.
당장의 문제에 맞는 LLM을 어떻게 고르죠?
And that is the main theme of this week.
그게 이번 주의 주요 주제죠
And in addition we'll be going to be generating code building llms that write code for us in open source
추가로 오픈 소스 랜드에서 코드를 작성하는 llms를 생성할 거예요
land.
재미있을 거예요
Uh, what we're going to be doing today is getting cracking on this subject of how do you pick the right
오늘 우리가 할 일은 작업에 적합한 모델을 어떻게 고르느냐에
model for the task.
관한 거예요
We're going to be talking about attributes and benchmarks, and we're going to be using something called
특성과 벤치마크에 대해 얘기하고 오픈ml leaderboard라는
the Openml leaderboard, which is an amazing resource from Hugging Face to help you compare open source
걸 사용할 겁니다 얼굴을 끌어안고 오픈 소스 모델 비교를 돕는 놀라운 리소스죠
But first, of course, a moment to look at our eight weeks.
그 전에 먼저 8주간의 여정을 돌아보죠
We started over on the left.
왼쪽에서부터 시작했어요
We're going to finish over on the right.
오른쪽을 마무리할 거예요
In week one.
첫 주에요
We talked about all things frontier model and we compared a bunch of frontier LMS, six of them.
프런티어 모델에 관해 얘기하면서 프런티어 LMS를 6대나 비교했어요
In week two, we introduced UIs with Gradio agent ization and of course we played with Multi-modality
2주차에선 그래디오 에이전트화와 함께 UI를 소개했고 3주차엔 다중 양상을
week three.
다뤘죠
Last week we got stuck into open source with Hugging face.
지난주엔 얼굴 맞대고 오픈 소스나 찍었잖아요
We looked at the hub, we looked at the high level API, the pipelines, and then we looked at Tokenizers
허브와 상위 레벨 API 파이프라인, 토큰라이저 모델도 살펴봤습니다
and models and hopefully a lot came together in terms of really understanding how these chat interfaces
많은 도움이 됐기를 바랍니다 채팅 인터페이스가 어떻게 작동하고
work and how these sorts of lists of dictionaries end up being tokens, including special tokens fed
이런 종류의 사전 목록이 어떻게 토큰이 되는지에 대해서요 특별한 토큰을 llms나
into llms, LMS, resulting in the output the next predicted token.
LMS에 공급해 다음 예상 토큰을 결과로 내놓는 거죠
We get to week four about selecting LMS, and also the problem of generating code which which is going
LMS 선택에 관한 4주 차에 접어들었죠 코드 생성 문제도 있어요 아주 흥미로울
to be very interesting.
거예요
I hope week five is rag.
5주 차가 누더기였으면 좋겠어요
Week six is fine tuning.
6주 차에는 조율을 잘해야 해요
It's when we begin training.
훈련 시작부터요
Training on the frontier and then training open source and bringing it all together.
개척지에서 훈련하고 오픈 소스를 훈련해서 전부 합쳤어요
That is our eight week plan.
그게 8주 계획이에요
And so for today we're talking about comparing models, comparing LMS.
오늘은 모델과 LMS 비교에 대해 얘기해보죠
And if there's one takeaway from this session, the most important point is that it's not like there's
이번 세션에서 얻은 교훈이 있다면 가장 중요한 점은 이 LLM이 다른 것보다
a simple answer of like this LLM is better than the others.
낫다는 간단한 답이 없다는 거예요
It isn't a a case of of ranking from best to worst.
이건 순위를 매기는 문제가 아니에요
It's all about what are you trying to accomplish.
무엇을 이루고 싶은지가 중요하죠
And it's about picking the right LLM for the task at hand.
작업에 적합한 LLM을 고르는 것도 중요하죠
So understanding weighing up different LMS and comparing them with your requirements is the name of
다른 LMS를 저울질하고 요구 사항과 비교하는 게 게임 이름입니다
the game, and there are two different ways that we can pair models.
모델을 쌍으로 연결하는 두 가지 다른 방법이 있어요
The first of them is looking just at the basic facts about the model.
첫 번째는 모델에 대한 기본적인 사실이죠
Um, obvious stuff like the cost of the model.
모델 가격 같은 뻔한 것들이요
Um, and that's going to really cut down your decision space into a smaller number of choices.
그러면 선택할 공간이 줄어들어요 선택지가 줄어들죠
And once you've investigated the sort of basic attributes, the basic aspects of the different models,
다양한 모델의 기본 속성과 기본 측면을 조사하고 나면
then then you start looking at the detailed results.
상세한 결과를 보기 시작하죠
And that involves looking at things like benchmarks, leaderboards and arenas.
벤치마크, 리더보드 경기장을 살펴봐야 해요
And based on all of this, you should end up with a handful of candidate llms that you will then use
이 모든 걸 기반으로 여러분은 소수의 후보 llms를 갖게 됩니다 시제품
for prototyping to allow you to finally select the best LLM for your task at hand.
제작에 사용하여 당면한 작업에 최적의 LLM을 선택할 수 있도록 하죠
And so let's talk a bit about the basics.
그럼 기본 비트부터 살펴보죠
So when I say we're comparing the basics, I really do mean the most obvious things about different
제가 기초를 비교한다고 했을 때 다른 모델에서 평가해야 할 가장 명백한
models that you would have to assess.
점을 말하는 거예요
And we start with understanding whether or not you're going to be looking at an open source model or
먼저 여러분이 오픈 소스 모델을 볼 건지 비공개 소스 모델을 볼 건지 이해해야
a closed source model.
해요
And of course, there are pros and cons, and it will affect a lot of the other basic attributes.
물론 장단점이 있고 다른 기본 속성에 영향을 미치겠죠
So as you develop your shortlist, the first thing to note down is is this open or closed source?
최종 목록을 만들 때 가장 먼저 기억해야 할 건 소스 공개냐, 폐쇄냐죠
When was it released?
언제 출시됐죠?
What is the release date and and presumably the same the same dates.
개봉일이 언제고 아마 같은 날짜일 거예요
But an important thing to note is what is the knowledge cutoff?
하지만 중요한 건 지식의 제한이 얼마냐는 거죠
What is the date?
날짜가 언제죠?
The last date of its training data, beyond which typically it won't have any knowledge of current events.
훈련 데이터의 마지막 날짜입니다 그 이후에는 현재 사건에 대한 지식이 전혀 없죠
And depending on your use case, that may be important to you or it might not.
사용 사례에 따라 중요할 수도 있고 아닐 수도 있죠
Then the number of parameters.
다음은 매개 변수의 수죠
This gives you a sense of the the strength of the model.
모델의 힘이 느껴질 거예요
It will also give you a strength of costs that will come to, and it will give you a sense of how much
또한 앞으로의 비용에 대한 확신을 줄 수 있고 훈련 데이터가 얼마나 필요한지
training data is needed.
알 수 있죠
If you want to fine tune that model, which we will also talk about in just a moment.
모델을 조정하고 싶다면 잠시 후에 다시 이야기하도록 하죠
So the number of parameters, the size of the model is another of the basic facts that you would note
모델의 크기 같은 매개변수의 개수는 훈련에서 사용된
down The number of tokens that were used during training.
패의 개수를 기록하는 것과 같죠
The size of the training dataset is an important thing to note, and it will give you a sense again
훈련 데이터셋의 크기는 중요한 겁니다 모델의 힘과 수준, 전문성의
of the power of the model, its level, its depth of expertise, and then of course, the context length,
깊이를 다시 한 번 느끼게 될 겁니다 물론 컨텍스트 길이 컨텍스트 창의 크기도요
The thing we spoke about a lot in the past.
예전에 자주 얘기했던 거요
The total amount of tokens that it can keep effectively in its memory while it's predicting the next,
메모리에 효과적으로 저장할 수 있는 토큰의 총량을 계산하고 다음 토큰을 예측할 수 있습니다.
next token, which needs to include the original system, prompt input prompts.
이 토큰에는 기존 시스템인 입력 프롬프트가 있어야 하는데요.
And if you're in a in a instruct in a chat use case, then all of the exchanges between the user and
채팅방 사용 사례를 보면 사용자와 보조 사이의 모든 익스체인지가
the assistant all have to fit within the context length.
컨텍스트 길이에 맞아야 하죠
If you're dealing with a multi shot prompting case where you're you're providing multiple examples at
Multi Shot PRpting을 사용할 때 모델을 추론할 시간에
inference time for the model to learn from, then you need to make sure that you're going to have a
여러 개의 예제를 제공한다면 이 예제들을 받아들이기에
sufficient context length to take all of those examples.
충분한 컨텍스트 길이를 가지고 있는지 확인해야 해요
Can you remember the model with the longest context length today?
오늘 컨텍스트 길이가 가장 긴 모델이 뭐였죠?
uh, Gemini 1.5 flash with a million size contacts window as of right now, but we'll see in a moment
제미니 1호요 지금은 백만 개 크기의 연락처 창이 있지만 곧
where you can go and look up and compare all of the context lengths.
살펴볼 거예요 모든 컨텍스트 길이를 비교할 수 있죠
So that's one set of basics.
이게 기본이고요
Let's go on to some more basics that you would you would look at.
여러분이 살펴볼 만한 기본으로 넘어가 보죠
So there's a bunch of of costs that you need to be mindful of.
고려해야 할 비용이 아주 많아요
I've divided them into inference costs, training costs and build costs.
조사 비용, 훈련 비용 건축 비용으로 나눴어요
So inference costs of course is how much is it going to cost you every time you run this model in production
추론 비용은 물론 프로덕션에서 이 모델을 실행할 때마다 입력된 산출물을 생성하기
to generate an output given an input?
위해 드는 비용은 얼마일까요?
That, put simply, is what we're talking about with inference.
간단히 말하자면요. 추측성으로 말하는 거예요.
Um, and there depending on whether you're dealing with open or closed source or and how you're interacting,
오픈 소스를 다루느냐 폐쇄 소스를 다루느냐 상호 작용 방식에 따라 비용이 여러 가지
there could be a number of different types of costs.
유형으로 발생할 수 있어요
We know, of course, with frontier models, we're thinking about API costs, which we also know consists
물론 프런티어 모델에서는 API 비용을 고려합니다 입력 토큰과
of a count of input tokens and output tokens that would need to go into that API cost.
출력 토큰의 개수로 구성되어 있는데 API 비용에 들어가는 것이죠
Uh, if you were talking about using the Pro user interfaces, the chat UIs, you'd be thinking of a
Pro 사용자 인터페이스나 채팅 UI를 사용하는 것에 대해 얘기할 때 구독을
subscription, a monthly subscription cost.
생각하게 됩니다 월간 구독 비용이죠
And if you're talking about open source models that you would run yourself, then there would be some
여러분이 직접 실행하는 오픈 소스 모델에 관해 얘기한다면 런타임
runtime compute cost, which could be like a colab cost, or later we'll be talking in the actually
계산 비용이 있을 겁니다 Colab 비용과 비슷하죠 프로덕션으로 배포하는
in probably the last week of this course about ways to deploy to production.
방법에 관해 이 과정의 마지막 주에 얘기할 거예요
Thinking about platforms like modal, which let you run your model in production on a GPU box, and
GPU 박스에서 프로덕션에서 모델을 실행하게 해주는 Modal 같은 플랫폼을
then you're paying some, uh, some, some fee to run your compute box in their cloud.
생각해보면 클라우드에서 계산 상자를 실행하는 데 약간의 비용을 지불하게 되죠
So that runtime compute for open source is another factor.
오픈 소스를 위한 계산 런타임도 또 다른 요소죠
And typically if you're if you're working with an open source model that you've trained yourself, your
일반적으로 여러분이 여러분이 직접 훈련한 오픈 소스 모델로 작업하는 경우 추론 비용은
inference costs will be lower because it's your model.
낮아집니다 여러분 모델이니까요
You're not going to be paying that API charge every time.
매번 API 비용을 지불하지 않아도 돼요
But there's you know, it's not a clear calculus.
하지만 명확한 계산은 아니에요
It depends on your use case.
사용 사례에 따라 다르죠
It depends on your choice of model, how many parameters and so on.
모델 선택과 매개 변수 개수에 따라 달라요
And then training cost.
훈련 비용도 있고요
So obviously if you're using out of the box frontier model, then there isn't a training cost.
틀에 박히지 않은 개척자 모델을 사용하면 훈련비가 안 들어요
If you're not further fine tuning it, as we'll do in week seven.
7주 차에 할 건데 더 세밀하게 조정하지 않으면요
But if you're doing, uh, building an open source model that you want to specialize for your domain
하지만 여러분의 도메인에 특화하고 싶은 오픈 소스 모델을 구축하는데
and you're going to be providing it with, with training costs, with, with, with training, then
거기에 교육 비용을 추가한다면 그에 따른 비용이 발생하겠죠
And you need to factor that into the equation.
그것도 고려해야 해요
Build cost.
공사비요
So how much work will it be for you to create this solution.
이 솔루션을 만드는 데 얼마나 많은 일이 필요할까요?
Uh, and that's highly related to the next one which is time to market, which is how long is it going
다음 제품과 밀접한 관련이 있어요 다음 제품은 출시까지 얼마나 걸릴까요?
Uh, the, the one of the selling points of using a frontier model.
개척지 모델을 쓰는 것의 장점 중 하나죠
Is that the time to market?
지금이 시장철인가요?
And the build cost can be very low.
건축 비용은 아주 낮을 수 있죠
Uh, it can take very little time to be up and running with a powerful solution using frontier models.
개척 시대 모델을 이용한 강력한 해결책을 실행하려면 시간이 아주 오래 걸리지 않아요
Typically, if you're looking to fine tune your own open source model, it's going to take longer and
일반적으로, 여러분 고유의 오픈 소스 모델을 세밀하게 조정하려는 경우 더 오래 걸리고
it's going to be harder.
더 어려워지죠
Uh, so that's that's a major factor to weigh up rate limits using frontier models, you may run into
그게 선구 모델의 속도 제한을 높이는 데 중요한 요소입니다 제한에 부딪힐
some limits on how frequently you can call them.
수도 있어요
This is typically the case for subscription plans.
구독 플랜의 전형적인 경우죠
Um, and uh, maybe, maybe with rate limits.
요금 제한도 포함해서요
I point out reliability as well when using the frontier models through the APIs.
API를 통한 프론티어 모델을 사용할 때도 신뢰성을 강조하죠
There are times when some of the models I've experienced this with both, uh, GPT four and with Claude
이런 경험을 한 모델들이 있어요 GPT
3.5 sonnet that the the, uh, APIs respond with an error that they are overloaded because they are
4와 클로드 3 둘 다요 5개의 소네트 API가 에러에 반응하는데 과부하가 걸렸다는 거죠
too busy in production at that time.
당시엔 생산하느라 너무 바빴거든요
So that's sort of related to rate limit, but a sort of stability point, their speed, which is a sort
속도 한계에 관한 것이고 안정점과 속도도 있습니다 처리량과 관련된 것입니다 전체
of throughput, like how quickly can you generate a whole response, how quickly can new tokens be generated?
응답을 생성하는 데 얼마나 걸릴까요? 새 토큰을 생성하는 데 얼마나 걸릴까요?
And very similar.
아주 비슷하죠
There's a sort of subtle distinction between speed and latency, which is sort of the request response
속도와 대기 시간 사이에는 미묘한 차이가 있어요 요청 응답 시간 같은
time.
거죠
When you ask how quickly does it first start responding with each token?
토큰 하나에 얼마나 빨리 반응하는지 물으면요?
You may remember when we built the AI assistant for our airline, which was multimodal and spoke back
기억하실지 모르겠지만 저희 항공사의 인공지능 보조 멀티모달에서 저희에게 말을 걸었어요
Latency was a bit of a problem there.
대기 시간이 문제였어요 비트
I don't think I mentioned it at the time, but there were some awkward pauses because of course when
그때 언급 안 한 것 같은데 어색한 침묵이 흘렀어요 텍스트가
there's some text, it's then going out to the model.
뜨면 모델로 가니까요
It's calling out to a frontier model, generating the audio, coming back and playing the audio.
개척자 모델을 불러내서 음향을 생성하고 돌아와서 재생하죠
And it was even more jarring when we were generating images, because those images were taking some
이미지를 생성할 때는 더 힘들었어요 이미지가 돌아오는 데 시간이 좀 걸렸고
time to come back and we'd sit there waiting for the image.
우리는 앉아서 이미지를 기다려야 했거든요
Obviously, there are ways to to handle that more gracefully than we did in our prototype, but that
물론 프로토타입보다 더 우아하게 다룰 방법은 있지만 반드시
is a factor that has to be.
그래야만 하는 요소죠
Bear in mind if you're dealing with your own open source model, it's the sort of thing you have more
자신의 오픈 소스 모델을 다루고 있다면 여러분이 더 통제할 수 있다는
control over.
걸 기억하세요
And then last of our basics, but definitely not least, is license.
마지막으로 기본이지만 가장 중요한 건 라이선스예요
Whether you're dealing with open source or closed source.
오픈 소스든 비공개 소스든 말이에요
You need to be fully aware of any license restrictions in terms of where you are, and are not allowed
라이선스 제한을 잘 아셔야 합니다 여러분이 있는 곳과 사용 금지라는 측면에서요
Um, many of the open source models have very open licensing.
많은 오픈 소스 모델은 오픈 라이선싱을 갖고 있어요
Um, some of them do have fine print.
작은 글씨가 있는 것도 있어요
I think stable diffusion is one that's known that that, uh, um, you are allowed to use it commercially
안정적인 확산이라는 건 상업적으로 어느 정도 사용할 수 있다는
up to a point.
뜻인데요
There's a point at which when your revenues are above a certain level, um, that at that point some,
귀사의 수입이 일정 수준을 넘으면 안정적으로
some kind of an arrangement business arrangement with stable diffusion, uh, is, is needed.
확산하는 일종의 계약 사업 협약이 필요한 시점이죠
Um, and we experienced ourselves signing the terms of service with, um, with llama 3.1 with meta.
라마 3과 함께 서비스 약관에 서명하는 경험을 했어요 메타 1이요
Uh, again, which I think is mostly to make sure that we're using it for good purposes, but still,
좋은 목적으로 사용하고 있는지 확인하기 위한 것이지만 라이선스의
it's part of the license that one needs to be aware of.
일부라는 걸 알아야 해요
So that wraps up the basics.
자, 기본은 다 됐고요
These are all things that you would note down before going in to a more detailed analysis of the performance,
성능을 더 자세히 분석하기 전에 기록해야 할 것들이죠 작업에 필요한
the accuracy of the models for the task at hand.
모델의 정확성도 마찬가지고요
And we will continue in the next session.
다음 시간에 계속하죠